# Julian Busch

I'm a PhD student in computer science at the Database Systems and Data Mining (DBS) group at LMU Munich, working on various topics in machine learning. My research focuses on learning representations of complex data, including graphs and high-dimensional data.

My areas of expertise include, but are not limited to, machine learning, deep learning, data mining, data science, artificial intelligence, big data management and analytics, and algorithm design.

I have 5+ years of research experience and 2+ years of experience working in industry and with industrial partners.







## **Education**

04/2016 - 07/2021 (expected)

Dr. rer. nat. (PhD) Computer Science

LMU Munich, Munich, Germany Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Thomas Seidl

#### 10/2013 - 03/2016

#### M.Sc. Computer Science

RWTH Aachen University, Aachen, Germany

Minor: Mathematics

Thesis supervisor: Prof. Dr. Thomas Seidl GPA: 3.9/4.0 (German grading system: 1.30)

#### 10/2009 - 09/2013

#### **B.Sc. Computer Science**

University of Hamburg, Hamburg, Germany

Minor: Applied Bioinformatics

Thesis supervisor: Prof. Dr. Ulrike von Luxburg GPA: 4.0/4.0 (German grading system: 1.12)

Awarded as best bachelor graduate

# **Experience**

04/2016 - present

**LMU Munich** - Research Assistant Database Systems and Data Mining Group *Munich, Germany* 

#### 05/2021 - 06/2021

**Kiel University** - Visiting Scholar Information Systems and Data Mining Group *Kiel, Germany* 

#### 04/2019 - 09/2019

## Siemens Corporate Technology - Research Intern

Research Group for Big Data and AI Technology for Business Analytics and Monitoring *Princeton, NJ, USA* 

#### 11/2018 - 12/2018

**George Mason University** - Visiting Scholar Department of Geography and Geoinformation Science Fairfax, VA, USA

#### 05/2015 - 02/2016

**RWTH Aachen University** - Student Research Assistant

Data Management and Data Exploration Group *Aachen, Germany* 

## 12/2010 - 03/2011

**University of Hamburg** - Student Teaching Assistant

Discrete Mathematics Group Hamburg, Germany

## **Industry Projects**

Third-party funded research projects at LMU Munich.

#### 03/2018 - 09/2018

Explanation of Classification Results on Multivariate Time Series by Convolutional Neural Networks

Siemens AG

## 09/2017 - 02/2018

#### **Data-driven Methods for Pre-Ignition Cause Analysis**

IAV Automotive Engineering GmbH

Supervised external master theses at LMU Munich.

## 07/2020 - 01/2021

Federated ClusterGAN: Latent Space Clustering on Decentralized Datasets

Rohde & Schwarz GmbH & Co. KG

## **Publications**

## NF-GNN: Network Flow Graph Neural Networks for Malware Detection and Classification

Julian Busch, Anton Kocheturov, Volker Tresp, and Thomas Seidl
International Conference on Statistical and Scientific Database Management (SSDBM), 2021

Best Paper Runner-Up Award

[pdf]

#### Learning Self-Expression Metrics for Scalable and Inductive Subspace Clustering

Julian Busch, Evgeniy Faerman, Matthias Schubert, and Thomas Seidl NeurIPS Workshop: Self-Supervised Learning - Theory and Practice, 2020 [pdf] [poster] [code]

# Ada-LLD: Adaptive Node Similarity for Node Classification Using Multi- Scale Local Label Distributions

Evgeniy Faerman, Felix Borutta, *Julian Busch*, and Matthias Schubert *IEEE/WIC/ACM International Joint Conference on Web Intelligence and Intelligent Agent Technology*(WI-IAT), 2020

Best Student Paper Award

[pdf]

#### Grace - Limiting the Number of Grid Cells for Clustering High-Dimensional Data

Anna Beer, Daniyal Kazempour, *Julian Busch*, Alexander Tekles, and Thomas Seidl *Conference on Learning, Knowledge, Data, and Analysis (LWDA)*, 2020 [pdf]

#### **PushNet: Efficient and Adaptive Neural Message Passing**

Julian Busch, Jiaxing Pi, and Thomas Seidl
European Conference on Artificial Intelligence (ECAI), 2020
[pdf] [slides] [talk] [code]

#### Structural Graph Representations based on Multiscale Local Network Topologies

Felix Borutta, *Julian Busch*, Evgeniy Faerman, Adina Klink, and Matthias Schubert *IEEE/WIC/ACM International Joint Conference on Web Intelligence and Intelligent Agent Technology (WI-IAT*), 2019
[pdf]

#### Semi-Supervised Learning on Graphs Based on Local Label Distributions

Evgeniy Faerman, Felix Borutta, *Julian Busch*, and Matthias Schubert *International Workshop on Mining and Learning with Graphs at ACM SIGKDD (MLG)*, 2018

[pdf]

#### **Towards Learning Structural Node Embeddings using Personalized PageRank**

Felix Borutta, *Julian Busch*, Evgeniy Faerman, and Matthias Schubert *Conference on Learning, Knowledge, Data, and Analysis (LWDA)*, 2017 [pdf]

# **Teaching Experience**

Teaching assistance at LMU Munich.

## Algorithm Design (Elite master's program Data Science)

Lecture

Winter 2019

#### **Big Data Management and Analytics**

Lecture

Winter 2017

#### **Innovation Lab Big Data Science**

Practical

Summer 2017

## **Knowledge Discovery in Databases I**

Lecture

Summer 2016, Winter 2018

#### **Knowledge Discovery in Databases II**

Lecture

Summer 2020

#### **Machine Learning**

Lecture

Summer 2018

#### **Recent Developments in Data Science**

Seminar

Winter 2016, Summer 2017, Summer 2021

## **Software Development Lab**

Practical

Summer 2016, Winter 2016, Winter 2020, Summer 2021

# **Supervised Theses**

Bachelor and master thesis supervision at LMU Munich.

2020

## **Neural Hough Transform for Subspace Clustering**

Master Thesis

**Generalized Neighborhood Aggregation for Graph Neural Networks** 

Bachelor thesis

#### Federated ClusterGAN: Latent Space Clustering on Decentralized Datasets

Master thesis

2019

**Neural End-To-End Subspace Clustering** 

Master thesis

**Spatio-Temporal Link Prediction** 

Bachelor thesis

**Inductive Subspace Clustering** 

Master thesis

2018

Recommendations on Dynamic Heterogeneous Networks with Metapath-RNNs

Master thesis

**Deep Conformance Checking** 

Bachelor thesis

**Graph Classification** 

Bachelor thesis

2017

**Dynamically Adapting Vertex Embeddings** 

Bachelor thesis

2016

Visualizing High-Dimensional Data with t-SNE

**Bachelor Thesis** 

**Accelerating Minimax Hierarchical Clustering** 

**Bachelor Thesis** 

## **Academic Service**

External reviews for academic conferences, journals and workshops.

- CIKM 2017, 2020
- Computers and Security 2021
- **DAMI** 2019, 2020, 2021
- **DSAA** 2018
- ECIR 2021
- EDBT 2018
- ICDE 2018
- **IDEA** 2016
- **KDD** 2019, 2020
- Machine Learning 2017
- Pattern Recognition 2020

## **Selected Skills**

#### Languages

C, C++, CSS, HTML, Java, Latex, Markdown, Matlab, Python, R, SQL

#### Frameworks

Bokeh, DGL, Keras, MLflow, Matplotlib, NetworkX, Numba, NumPy, Pandas, PyTorch, PyTorch Geometric, Scikit-Learn, SciPy, Seaborn, Spark, Tensorflow

#### Tools

Docker, Git, Linux, Slurm

#### Soft Skills

Certificate of advanced training in self-management, leadership and teaching skills awarded by the LMU Center for Leadership and People Management

## **Natural Languages**

German (native), English (proficiency), Latin (Latinum), Mandarin (beginner), French (beginner)